Guide to the Algernon David Black Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series V: Pamphlets
  - Subseries V.1: Published under auspices of N.Y. Society for Ethical Culture and/or American Ethical Union:
    - C. Discrimination and Civil Rights
      - Anti-Semitism: Is There an Answer? (1938) (Box 6)
      - The City's Children and the Challenge of Racial Discrimination (1958) (Box 6)
    - D. Politics and Democracy
      - Democracy and Ethical Culture (late 1930s) (Box 6)
      - War and the Individual -- Is Pacifism the Answer? (ca. 1937) (Box 6)
      - War and the Democratic Spirit ( September 13, 1932 - A.D. Black and J. Nathanson) (Box 6)
      - The Road Ahead (October 30, 1938) (Box 6)
      - Can We Save America's Freedom? (March 29, 1953) (Box 6)
    - E. Family, Children
      - The Religious Education of the Child (2 editions: 1930s and revised edition ca. 1950) (Box 6)
      - Ethics of Birth Control (1936) (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous
      - Memorial for Benjamin Cohen (A.D.B. and other speakers -March 1960) (Box 6)
  - Subseries V.2: Non-Ethical Society pamphlets
    - A. Public Affairs Committee:
      - If I Marry Outside My Religion (2 editions: 1954 -#204; and revised version 1967 -#204A) (Box 6)
      - Who's My Neighbor? (October 1958 -#273) and edition: Fair Play in Housing --Who's My Neighbor? (1966 -#396) (Box 6)
    - B. Discrimination
      - Ethical Issues of the Armenian Question (1936 reprinted from The Standard) (Box 6)
- Series VI: Miscellaneous Publications
  - Subseries VI: 1. Ethical Culture
    - Ethical News: "War and Human Conscience II (April 1, 1962) (Box 6)
    - Ethical Religion Speaks: "Soviet Achievement: Implications for America" (December 15, 1957) (Box 6)
    - The Humanist: "Civil Rights and Ethical Responsibilities" (April 1951) (Box 6)
    - Ideals at Work: "United Nations Greeted by Ethical Leaders" (December 1955) Morality and American Freedom (Book, with selections by leaders of Ethical Culture Society) (1972) (Box 6)
    - News Letter, New York Society for Ethical Culture: "An Easter Message" (April 1957) (Box 6)
    - The Standard: "The Rights of Children" (October 1934) (Box 6)
    - "An Approach to Moral Education" (November 1937) (Box 6)
    - "Ethical Religion and Youth" (May or June, 1939') (Box 6)
    - "The Ethical Movement and Human Experience" (February 1940) (Box 6)
    - "Ethical Societies Must Face the Future" (March 1944) (Box 6)
    - "The Armenian People" (March 1946) (Box 6)
    - "Divorce By Mutual Consent" (January 1949) (Box 6)
    - "The Case of Cardinal Mindszenty" (March 1949) (Box 6)
    - "You and World Religion" (Lyman Bryson & A.D.B. –November-December 1953) (Box 6)
  - Subseries VI: 2. Miscellaneous periodicals:
    - Church and Society:
      - Issue titled "Voluntary Parenthood", with articles by A.D. Black and Margaret Sanger and Hannah Stone. (February 1932) (Box 6)
    - The Churchman:
      - "Is Humanism Enough?" (June-July 1971) (Box 6)
    - The Journal of Intergroup Relations:
      - "The Quest for Community" (Winter 1959-60) (Box 6)
    - Child Study:
      - "Religious Education in the Ethical Movement" (February 1936) (Box 6)
      - "Youth and Citizenship Responsibility" (Summer 1942) (Box 6)
    - National Parent-Teacher:
      - "How Children Acquire Morale" (September 1951) (Box 6)
    - School Parent:
      - "What Are Youth Is Questions?" (October 1936) (Box 6)
    - School Volunteer News (Public Education Association):
      - "Helping the Child to Live and Learn: Challenge to the Citizens" (November 1963) (Box 6)
- Series VII: Books -- Algernon David Black
  - The People And The Police – Publisher McGraw-Hill., 1968 (Box 6)
  - The First Book Of Ethics --Publisher, Franklin Watts, Inc. 1965 (Box 6)
  - The Young Citizens, The Story of the Encampment for Citizenship, Publisher, Frederick Ungar, Co. 1962 (Box 6)
  - Without Burnt Offerings: Ceremonies of Humanism. Viking, 1974. (Box 6)
  - The Woman Of The Wood: A Tale from old Russia. Holt, Rinehart, Winston, 1973. (Box 6)
- Series VIII: Subject Files
  - Subseries VIII: 1 - Settlement Work
    - l. My first Settlement House Job -The Hudson Guild in Chelsea – Hell’s Kitchen" 1923 (Box 17)
    - 2. Hudson Guild -Settlement House (Box 17)
    - 3. My Work: at Madison House Settlement -1926-1930 (Box 17)
    - 4. Madison House Settlement General (Appendix) (Box 17)
  - Subseries VIII: 2 - Labor Movement
    - 5. My Work in the Labor Movement (1) (Box 17)
    - 6. My Work in the Labor Movement•(2) (Box 17)
    - 7. My Work in the Labor Movement (3) (Box 17)
    - 8. West Virginia Children of the Coal Mines Project (Box 17)
  - Subseries VIII: 3: Birth Control
    - 9. Birth Control Movement -The Beginnings of My Involvement (1929-1930) (Box 18)
    - 10. Birth Control Movement -My Involvement thru 1940s (Box 18)
    - 11. Birth Control Involvement Welfare and Health Council of New York Crisis and Conflict - 1953. (Box 18)
    - 12. Birth Control Involvement - Activities in the 1950s. (Box 18)
    - 13. Birth Control Movement: - 1960s and 1970s (Box 18)
  - Subseries VIII: 4: Abortion Reform
    - 14. Abortion Reform Movement (Box 18)
    - 15. Movement for Voluntary Sterilization (Box 18)
    - 16. Abortion Reform Movement. BOX 19 (Box 18)
  - Subseries VIII: 5: "Subversive"-The McCarthy Era
    - 17. Subversive -"Guilt By Association" -The Beginnings (Box 19)
    - 18. Subversive -My "Respectabilities" or "Unlisted" organizations -Awards and Activities (Box 19)
    - 19. Subversive -House UnAmerican Activities Committee -Background. (Box 19)
    - 20. Attacks based on H.U.A.C. Listings. (Box 19)
    - 21. Subversive –H.U.A.C. Attacks -"Guilt by .Association" (Box 19)
    - 22. Subversive Examples of Activities with Organizations Listed by HUAC as subversive. (Box 19)
    - 23. Subversion – The Spanish Civil War (Box 19)
    - 24. The Spanish Civil War -Appendix (Box 19)
    - 25. Subversion -1939-1940 -Greater New York Conference on Inalienable Rights (Box 20)
    - 26. Subversion -Attack by a Newspaper -"The Tablet" (Box 20)
    - 27. Subversion - 1948 -"Tablet"/Youthbuilders Attack (Box 20)
    - 28. Subversive -Correspondence on Attack on The Encampment for Citizenship by H.U.A.C. (Box 20)
    - 29. Examples of Work, Social Activism, Community Action outside the The Ethical Society. (Box 20)
    - 30. Subversion -Freedom House -Controversy 1960 (Box 20)
    - 31. Subversive -1943-1949 –The Waldorf Conference Controversy (Box 20)
    - 32. Subversive -The Passport Incident (Box 21)
    - 33. Subversive The F.B..I. File (Box 21)
    - 34. Subversive - CIA File -1938 through Present (Box 21)
  - Subseries VIII: 6: Radio Experience
    - 35. My Radio Experiences (Box 21)
    - 36. Drafts and Samples of WQXR Scripts. (Box 21)
    - 37. My Radio Experience -Excerpts of Radio "Fan" Mail (Box 21)
    - 38. Radio Experience -Miscellaneous Scripts for Various Stations (Box 21)
    - 39. Radio Addresses by Other Leaders (Box 21)
  - Subseries VIII: 7: Experience In Indian Affairs
    - 40. Sabbatical Year and My Trip to the Reservations (1954) (Box 22)
    - 41. How I Became Involved• (Box 22)
    - 42. Appendix -Association on American Indian Affairs, Inc. (Box 22)
    - 43. A Visit to .Three Tribes -1954--The Menominee (Box 22)
    - 44. A Visit .to the Chippewa at Red Lake (Box 22)
    - 45. Stopover After Pine Ridge (Box 22)
    - 46. The Oglala Sioux at Pine Ridge (Box 22)
    - 47. My Report – Some Reflections (Box 22)
    - 48. Indian Affairs - Appendix (Box 22)
    - 49. Report of 1954 to the Menominee on Termination -and the Menominee Revisited in 1974. (Box 22)
  - Subseries VIII: 8: Study On Medicine
    - 50. Study on Discrimination in Medicine (1962-1963) (Box 22)
    - 51. Discrimination in Medicine -Appendix (Box 22)
    - 52. Special Projects -Study on Nurses 1962-1963 (Box 22)
    - 53. August 1972 -A Report on and Visit to Overboook, A State Correctional Institute for Boys, ages 8-12 New York. (Box 22)
  - Subseries VIII: 9: Work Camps for America
    - 54. Work Camps for America -1940-1941 (Box 23)
    - 55. Work Camps for America -Appendix (Copies of Various Minutes) (Box 23)
    - 56. Work Camps for America (Relationship with International Student Service) (Box 23)
  - Subseries VIII: 10: Encampment for Citizenship
    - 57. Encampment for Citizenship -Its Beginnings, Purposes & General Background (Box 23)
    - 58. Encampment for Citizenship -The Campers (Box 23)
    - 59. Encampment for Citizenship -The Campers -What They Think They Got and What They Did (Box 23)
    - 60. Encampment for Citizenship -Faculty and Staff (Box 23)
    - 61. Encampment for Citizenship -Staff Handbook (Box 23)
    - 62. Encampment for Citizenship -Staff Evaluation of the Encampment (Box 24)
    - 63. Encampment for Citizenship -Educational Program Outlines (1940s 50s,60s) (Box 24)
    - 64. Encampment for Citizenship -Workshops (Box 24)
    - 65. Encampment for Citizenship -International Workshops (Box 24)
    - 66. Encampment for Citizenship Lectures (Box 24)
    - 67. Encampment for Citizenship Educational Policies Committee (Box 25)
    - 63. Encampment for Citizenship -Constitution Meetings/Finance (Box 25)
    - 69. Encampment for Citizenship -Educational Policy Committee (Box 25)
    - 70. Encampment for Citizenship -The Berkeley Encampment (1953-1959-1960) (Box 25)
    - 71. Encampment for Citizenship -Puerto Rico Encampment (1959-1961) (Box 25)
    - 72. Encampment for Citizenship -Puerto Rico Encampments (1962-1969) (Box 25)
    - 73. Encampment for Citizenship "The Young Citizens" -Response to my Letter -1959-1960 (Box 25)
    - 74. Encampment for Citizenship -Alumni Letters (Box 26)
    - 75. Encampment for Citizenship -Individual Stories (Box 26)
    - 75. Encampment for Citizenship -Peace Corps (Box 26)
  - Subseries VIII:11 –New York City Police/Civilian~ Complaint Review Board {1966)
    - 77. Civilian. Complaint. Review Board - (l) (Box 26)
    - 78. Civilian Complaint Review Board - (2) (Box 26)
    - 79. Civilian Complaint Review Board - (3) (Box 26)
    - 80. Civilian Complaint Review Board - (4) (Box 26)
    - 8l. Civilian Complaint Review Board - (5) (Box 26)
    - 82. Civilian Complaint Review Board - (6) (Box 26)
  - Subseries VIII:12 -Personalities -As I Remember Them
    - 83. Eleanor Roosevelt (Box 27)
    - 84. Dr. Albert Einstein and Dr. J.Robert Oppenheimer (Box 27)
    - 85. Senator George Metcalf, Frances Levenson, Dr. George Cannon Congressman Earl Brown, "Nanny" Pollitzer (Box 27)
    - 86. Robert Kennedy, Martin Luther King, Dorothy Norman, Monsignor Cornelius J. Drew. (Box 27)
    - 87. Leopold Stowkowski, Walter White, Jackie Robinson. (Box 27)
    - School Study (Box 27)
    - Special Study-Negroes in TV (Box 27)